Vineeth Venugopal

Email: vineethcvenugopal@gmail.com

Phone: +91-9886254591

Self-driven IT professional with more than 7 and 1/2 years of experience in DevOps, system administration, technical troubleshooting, team building and infrastructure setup & maintenance. Broad and hands-on experience with open source applications and technologies.

Professional Experience

Current Employer:- Carmatec IT Solutions Pvt. Ltd.

Carmatec is an offshore, end to end IT Solutions provider for SMBs across the globe.

DevOPs Engineer (September 2016 - Till date)

Roles and responsibilities

- Automating and maintaining Cloud infrastructure for Development/QA/Staging/Production Deployments.
- Provisioning of EC2 instances, Security Group policies, IAM, Route 53, S3 etc using terraform.
- Using Chef and terraform to automate, provision and manage infrastructure, services and applications.
- Setup monitoring, alerting and metrics scraping for java/scala/play applications using prometheus and Graylog2 integrated with PagerDuty and Hipchat for alerts.
- Setup automated deployment pipeline for micro-services in an IOT cloud platform.
- 24x7 On-call support for production incidents.

Infrastructure Specialist (Jan 2016 - September 2016)

Roles and responsibilities

- As part of the IT infrastructure team, helped maintain and administrate the in-house applications, hardware, and network environment.
- Establish and document IT work-flows for internal users.
- Setup accounts, ACLs, manage email groups for users.
- Backup strategy and data replication for clients.

- Provisioning AWS Infrastructure comprising of services EC2, S3, ELB, EBS, AutoScaling, Route53 for customers
- Worked with development team to provide appropriate cloud solutions and support during production deployments.
- Created an automated deployment pipeline for the in-house dev team for faster product delivery.

Designation: - Client Service Manager (March 2014 - Jan 2016)

Roles and responsibilities

- Managing a team of L1, L2 & L3 system administrators.
- Developing customer service policies, procedures and standards.
- Provided qualitative and quantitative analysis of help desk tickets and customer surveys to gauge user satisfaction.
- Authored help desk articles for external user-base and internal documentation
- Training Sales and Support department on help desk and email support procedures.
- Oversaw the expansion of a 5 member team to 14 members.

Designation: - Sr. Systems Administrator (February 2010 - February 2014)

Roles and responsibilities

- Managing, monitoring and configuring linux servers and providing infrastructure solutions to domestic and overseas clients.
- Provide customer facing support to web hosting customers in a fast paced quality driven environment. Handled live chat, phone calls, and tickets.
- Installation, configuration, maintenance of a LAMP stack.
- MySQL installation, clustering, performance tuning and management.
- Package management using RPM, Debian package manager.
- Server audits and monitoring tools configuration and management.
- Website migration.
- Configuring DNS and DHCP servers.
- Fine-tuning of common performance issues.
- Troubleshooting/Installation/Upgrades: apache, mysql, ftp, DNS, email and cPanel.
- Handling abuse complaints from DCs and providing server abuse monitoring.
- Server monitoring | Nagios Client- Server configuration.
- Part of internal QC and training group.
- Managing firewall and security.
- Managing DNS zones on standalone and cluster servers, troubleshooting DNS resolution issues.

Designation:- Technical Trainer

Responsibilities

- Provide training in Basic/advanced linux, LAMP concepts, AWS Cloud and DevOps tools.
- Soft Skills Training.

Key Skills and Expertise

- Platforms:- Centos, Ubuntu.
- Virtualization:- KVM, Xen.
- Containers:- Docker, OpenVZ.
- Cloud:- AWS
- AWS services:- EC2, EBS, S3, Route53, Cloudfront, SG, IAM, RDS
- Microservices:- Apache Mesos, Marathon, Chronos, Zookeeper
- Service Discovery:- Consul
- Cl build tools:- Jenkins
- Configuration Management:- Chef
- Revision conrol:- Git
- Provisioning:- Terraform
- Centralized Logging:- Rsyslog, Logstash, graylog
- NoSQL:- Cassandra, Elasticsearch
- Message Broker:- Kafka
- Proxies:- HaProxy
- Firewall:- lptables, Config Server Firewall.
- Disk Management: LVM, RAID
- Webservers:- Apache, Nginx.
- DNS:- BIND, powerDNS.
- System/Network Monitoring:- Nagios/Check MK Prometheus.
- Email:- Exim, Courier IMAP, Dovecot.
- RDBMS:- MySQL
- FTP Servers:- Pure-Ftpd, Vsftpd.
- Security Tools:- AlienVault, clamAV, Rkhunter, Chkrootkit.
- Scripting:- BASH
- Scheduling Cron, Chronos

Education

Bachelor of Engineering (Electronics and Communication) - BTL Institute of Technology - (VTU University)

Personal Details

Name:- Vineeth Venugopal
Father's name:- C. Venugopal
Date of Birth:- 26-08-1985

Linguistics:- English, Hindi, Malayalam and Kannada

Address:- #1376, 2nd Floor, HSR layout, Sector -1, 21st 'A' main, 10th cross, Bangalore 560102